Finding Aid for Gilchrist Family Papers 1867-1945
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Ralph and Frank Gilchrist
  - Gilchrist Timber Company
    Gilchrist Timber Company records is small file containing the financial statements and some legal papers of this Oregon-based company, headed by Frank W. Gilchrist II.
    - Financial Statements 1937-1938 (Box 4)
- Ralph E. Gilchrist
  Following the death of his brother Frank and the marriage of his sister, Ralph E. Gilchrist assumed primary responsibility managing the Gilchrist enterprises. The Ralph E. Gilchrist series includes a general correspondence subseries and subseries for a number of companies in which he had an interest.
  - General Correspondence
    General Correspondence is a group of letters pertaining largely to Ralph's role in the settlement of the Frank W. Gilchrist estate. Much of the material relates to the sale of Alpena Portland Cement Company, the purchase of the Hecla Cement Company, the sale of Merida Shipping Company, and the establishment of Gilchrist & Company Limited. The letters also reflect the division in the Gilchrist family between William A. Gilchrist and the other Gilchrist heirs. Correspondents include William, Frank R., and Ralph Gilchrist.
    - 1911-1926 (Box 5)
  - Oregon Lands
    The Oregon Lands subseries is a group of letters, reports, and related documents pertaining to Ralph Gilchrist's acquisition of real estate in Crook, Klamath, and Lake Counties, Oregon. Principal correspondents include Patrick Culligan, a Gilchrist agent.
    - Correspondence 1909-1915 (Box 5)
    - Reports 1902-1923 (Box 5)
  - Merida Steamship Company
    Merida Steamship Company includes letters and financial statements pertaining largely to the financial operations of the Company and of the F. W. Gilchrist estate. Included are company financial statements for the years 1901, 1902, and 1907-1916, as well as statements pertaining to the steamer Joseph W. Fordney.
    - Correspondence 1914-1919 (Box 5)
    - Statements 1901-1919 (Box 5)
  - Minnesota Lands and Mineral Rights
    The Minnesota Lands and Mineral Rights subseries is large assortment of document consisting primarily of correspondence but also of deeds, maps, and related legal materials pertaining to the acquisition and liquidation of property in Lake, St. Louis, and Koochichiny Counties, Minnesota. Correspondents include Ralph Gilchrist, Harry Fletcher, Frank J. Foley, Joseph A. Vance, and several state officials of Minnesota.
    - Correspondence
      - 1910-1914 (Box 5)
      - 1928 (Box 5)
      - 1929 (Box 5)
      - 1930 (Box 5)
      - 1931-1935 (Box 5)
      - 1937 (Box 5)
      - 1938 (Box 5)
      - 1939 (Box 5)
      - 1940 (Box 5)
      - 1941-1949 (Box 5)
    - Assorted Deeds 1905-1940 (Box 5)
    - Assorted Maps undated (Box 5)
  - Zinclands
    Zinclands consists of correspondence, financial statements, deeds, and maps pertaining to Ralph Gilchrist's role as trustee of family-owned property in Newton County, Arkansas.
    - Correspondence 1911-1917 (Box 5)
    - Financial Statements and Maps 1917-1921 (Box 5)
  - Alpena Portland Cement Company
    The Alpena Portland Cement Company subseries is a group of records pertaining to a company acquired by Frank W. Gilchrist and disposed of by his heirs. The material includes two bound books containing company minutes, and a folder consisting primarily of legal documents. Correspondence regarding this company may be found in the Ralph Gilchrist General Correspondence file.
    - Minute Books
      - 1899-1905 (Box 5)
      - 1905-1916 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous Deeds and Minutes 1904-1916 (Box 5)
  - Thunder Bay Limestone Company
    Thunder Bay Limestone Company records include minutes, financial statements, and some correspondence pertaining to this Alpena-based quarry. The minutes, from a previously-bound spiral book, date from 1899-1916, and the correspondence is somewhat later, dating from 1919-1926. Principal correspondents include Ralph Gilchrist and Frank J. Foley.
    - Correspondence and Stockholders Lists 1919-1936 (Box 6)
    - Minutes 1919-1926 (Box 6)
    - Deeds and Maps 1919-1923 (Box 6)
    - Tax Case Records 1926-1930 (Box 6)
  - Dominion Sugar Company
    The Dominion Sugar Company subseries is a group of records pertaining to a Chatham, Ontario company headed by Ralph Gilchrist. The papers include correspondence of Ralph and legal materials relating to the merger of the company with the Canada Sugar Refining Company in 1930. Also included are director's reports, notices, and financial statements.
    - Correspondence and Reports 1923-1930 (Box 6)
  - Personal Financial Investments
    Personal Financial Investments is a diverse group of records that relate to Ralph Gilchrist's investments in the Crittall Casement Window Company from 1922 to 1928, the Detroit Trust Company from 1926 to 1934, Commonwealth Securities Incorporated of Cleveland from 1928 to 1933, and the First National Bank of Detroit Depositor's Committee in 1934. This assortment of materials includes correspondence, financial statements, reports, and some legal documents pertaining to the ownership of stocks. Much of the material pertains to the management of investment companies during the time of the stock market crash of 1929.
    - Crittall Casement Window Company
      - Correspondence 1921-1928 (Box 6)
      - Daily Reports 1922-1928 (Box 6)
      - Monthly Reports 1922-1928 (Box 6)
      - Yearly Statements 1922-1927 (Box 6)
    - Detroit Trust Company, Correspondence and Reports 1926-1934 (Box 6)
    - Commonwealth Securities, Inc
      - Correspondence
        - 1929 (Box 6)
        - 1930 (Box 6)
        - 1931 (Box 6)
      - Financial Statements
        - 1928-1930 (Box 6)
        - 1931-1933 (Box 6)
    - Depositor's Committee, First National Bank, Correspondence 1934 (Box 6)
  - Gilchrist and Company, Limited
    The Gilchrist and Company, Limited series contains correspondence, reports, and financial statements regarding the corporation, investments, management, and dissolution of the umbrella company of Gilchrist operations. The company was created as a funnel for all of the real estate holdings of Ralph, Frank R., and Grace Gilchrist, three of the four surviving heirs of Frank W. Gilchrist. Correspondence is extant from 1914 to 1926 and from 1937 to 1941. Materials relate both the Company as well as to its related trust fund. Included in the files are materials on the Bay City, Gaylord, and Alpena Rail Road (a company investment)and the U.S. Department of Commerce. Correspondents include Frank J. Foley, Ralph Gilchrist, Harry Fletcher, and Frank R. Potter (a cousin). There is also a small file pertaining to Dr. Duncan A. Cameron, an acquaintance of Ralph to whom the family and company paid tribute in 1925.
    - General Correspondence
      - 1914-1922 (Box 7)
      - 1923-1926 (Box 7)
      - Letterpress Book 1924-1925 (Box 7)
      - 1937-1941 (Box 7)
    - Cameron Day Assorted Materials 1925-1929 (Box 7)
    - Frank J. Foley Correspondence
      - Department of Commerce
        - 1928 (Box 7)
        - 1929 (Box 7)
        - 1930 (Box 7)
      - Bay City, Gaylord and Alpena Rail Road 1918-1935 (Box 7)
    - Financial Statements
      - Yearly
        - 1914-1927 (Box 7)
        - 1928-1941 (Box 7)
      - Alpena Office
        - 1922-1932 (Box 7)
      - Trial Balances (Monthly)
        - 1926-1928 (Box 7)
        - 1929-1930 (Box 7)
        - 1931-1933 (Box 7)
        - 1934-1936 (Box 7)